Guide to the Gustave R. Sattig Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gustave Reinhold Sattig collection
1739-1930
MS 1429
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
This is a miscellaneous collection of letters and papers assembled by Gustave R. Sattig. The material falls into two broad divisions: Sattig's personal correspondence and papers, which include letters from George Dudley Seymour; and papers of historical interest, collected by Sattig, which mainly document the American Revolution and Civil War.
Sattig, Gustave Reinhold, 1876-1950
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gustave R. Sattig and his estate, 1946-1950. The collection was originally part of the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection, MS 352.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Gustave R. Sattig Collection is composed of Gustave Sattig's personal papers and collected materials including papers such as letters, financial records, and official documents relating to American history. The largest quantity of material is in folder 4, which contains 31 letters from George Dudley Seymour. The letters concern their mutual antiquarian interests. Papers collected by Sattig include individual items relating to several New England and mid-Atlantic states and autographed letters signed by Dorothea Dix, Peter Dumont Vroom, and Thurlow Weed.
Gustave Sattig and his estate donated these materials to the Yale Library in 1946, 1948, and 1950. The collection was transferred from the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection.
Biographical / Historical
Gustave Reinhold Sattig was born in 1876 and died on May 14, 1950. He was a member of the Yale Law School Class of 1903, but did not graduate. He lived in Guilford, Connecticut, and for half a century was considered an authority on American antiques.
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Sattig, Gustave Reinhold, 1876-1950; Seymour, George Dudley, 1859-1945
- Inventory
  - Papers of G.R. Sattig
    - Correspondence
      - Putnam, Nina Wilcox, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Sattig, Ottilie, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Sattig, Selma, estate, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Seymour, George Dudley, 1920-1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Tully, Elizabeth L., 1844, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Unidentified and miscellaneous, 1923, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Sketchbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Papers collected by G.R. Sattig
    - Accounts and correspondence re: military and wartime supplies in Connecticut, Maryland, Massachusetts, and New York, 1774-1781, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut. Freemasons. Grand Lodge: certificate issued to Chauncy Hall, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Coxall Family, of British West Indies and London: legal and financial papers, baptismal certificate, 1815-1816, 1836, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      General
      See also: MG Common Folio 59
    - Cuba. Governor: customs document issued to D.N. Thompson, [1867?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Haines, Daniel, family; letters from Dorothea Lynde Dix, William Samuel Pennington, William H. Penrose, U.S. Dept. of State, and Peter Dumont Vroom, 1860-1863 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Jackson, W.E.: letters from Washington Hesing and Joseph Cornelius Smith, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Kelsey, Isaac: ALS to Martha Willcocks, 1742 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Maryland: legal papers, 1746, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - New York. Governor (Edwin Denison Morgan): ALS to Thomas C. Doremus, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Obookiah, Henry: ALS to Samuel Wells, Jr., 1817 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rhode Island (Box 2)
      See: Inventory Folder MG Common Folio 59
    - Sweden. Legislation. Papal States: commission appointing Raffaele Adjnolfi an official in the legation's accounting office, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Virginia: legal papers, 1763, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Weed, Thurlow: ALS to Mary E. Gregory, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Whittelsey, Elisha: letter from F. Foley, and passport signed by the governor of Minnesota (Alexander Ramsey), 1860, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous poems, 1790, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Oversize
    - Coxall, John Cavalier: will, 1793 (Box 2)
    - Rhode Island: legal papers, 1739 (Box 2)